<appendix id="fdl-zh">

   <title>GNU 自由文档许可证</title>

    <para>声明
</para>

    <para>
	这不是 GNU 
自由文档许可证的正式中文译文。它不是由自由软件基金会发布的，它不具备 GNU Free Documentation License 的英文原文所具有的法律效力。但是希望此翻译能帮助说中文的人更好地理解 GNU 自由文档许可证。下一章即是 GNU Free Documentation License 的英文原文。

    </para>

    <para><literal>0.导言</literal>
</para>

    <para>
      本许可证着意于保证手册、教科书或其它文档的<quote>自由</quote>: 以确保任何人复制和重新发布这些文档的自由，不管在商业领域还是非商业领域，经过修改还是没有修改。其次，本许可证保证了文档作者和发行者可以因他们的工作而获得信誉，同时不必为其他人所作的修改而负责。

    </para>
    
    <para>
      本许可证是一种<quote>copyleft</quote>，其含义为:文档的衍生作品必须与原文档是同样自由的。本许可证是 GNU 通用公共许可证的补充，后者是为自由软件设计的一种 copyleft 许可证。

    </para>
    
    <para>
      我们设计本许可证供自由软件的手册使用，因为自由软件需要自由文档：自由软件必须附带有提供了软件所俱的同等自由的手册。不过本许可证的适用范围并不仅限于软件手册，所有的文本作品都可以使用本许可证，不管主题是什么或者是否以书本的形式发行。我们鼓励那些俱指导性质或参考性质的文档作品使用本许可证。 

    </para>

	<para><literal>1.适用范围和定义</literal>
</para>

    <para id="fdl-zh-document">
      本许可证应用于任何手册或其它作品，只要版权所有者在作品放置一条声明，说明使用本许可证的条款发布。下文中的<quote>Document（文档）</quote>都是指这样的手册或作品。任何一个人都是本许可证的许可对象，这里将用<quote>你</quote>来称呼。

    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-zh-modified">
      文档的<quote>Modified 
Version（修改版）</quote>是指任何包含全部或部分 Document 
的作品，不论是照搬照抄还是经过修改或是翻译成其它语言。 

    </para>
	
    <para id="fdl-zh-secondary">
      <quote>Secondary Section（从属章节）</quote>是指命名的附录或 
Document 的前序部分，专门描述 Document 的发行者或作者与 
Document 
的主题（或者与相关事项）之间的关系，并且包含文档主题之外的内容。（比如，如果 Document 是一本数学教科书的一部分，Secondary Section可能不会提到任何数学话题。）关系可以是与主题或相关事项的历史联系，或者有关它们的法律、商业、哲学、道德或政治立场。

    </para>

    <para id="fdl-zh-invariant">
      <quote>Invariant Sections（不可变章节）</quote>是指某些 Secondary 
Sections。在说明 Document 
是依本许可证发布的声明中，指明了这些 Secondary Sections 
属于 Invariant Sections。

    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-zh-cover-texts">
      <quote>Cover 
Texts（封面文字）</quote>是指某些小段文字。在说明 Document 
是依本许可证发布的声明中，指明了这些文字将以封面文字或封底文字列出。

    </para>
	
    <para id="fdl-zh-transparent">
      Document 
的<quote>Transparent</quote>副本是指计算机可读的副本，以一种公开规格的格式表达，其内容可以直接使用通用文本编辑器或（对于其中由像素构成的图片）使用通用绘画程序或（对于其中的绘图）使用一些被广泛应用的图像编辑器来浏览或者修改，并且适合作为文本格式化程序的 输入，或者适合被自动翻译成一些格式同时这些格式适合作为文本格式化程序的输入。如果一个副本是以一种可以阻挠读者的后续修改的非 Transparent 格式发布的，那么这就不是 Transparent 副本。一个非 <quote>Transparent</quote> 副本称之为 <quote>Opaque</quote> 副本。

    </para>
    
    <para>
      Transparent 副本适用的格式包括没有标记的纯 ASCII 
文本、Texinfo 格式、LaTeX 格式、使用公开的 DTD 的 SGML 或 
XML 以及符合标准的便于人修改的纯 HTML。Opaque 
格式包括PostScript、PDF、只能用商业字处理程序读写的专有格式、使用不易获得的 DTD 或处理工具的 SGML 或 XML 以及某些字处理程序产生的只用于输出目的的 HTML。

    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-zh-title-page">
      <quote>Title 
Page（扉页）</quote>，对于刊印成册的书，是指扉页本身及其后的几页，这几页要包含有本许可证要求在扉页里出现的清楚明了的资料。对于没有扉页的作品格式，<quote>Title Page</quote> 指的是靠近作品标题且在正文开始之前的文字。

    </para>
   
	<para><literal>2.原样复制</literal>
</para>

    <para>
      你可以在任何媒介上复制和发布 
Document，不论是用于商业或非商业目的，只要所有的副本都包括本 License、版权声明和说明本 License 应用于 Document的许可证声明，而且你不再加入任何其他类似的对于本 License 的条件。你不可以采取技术手段以妨碍或控制别人阅读或再复制你制作或发布的副本。不过，你可以发布副本以获取他人给你的一些补偿。如果你发布的副本数量大到一定程度，你必须符合第3节的条件。

    </para>
    
    <para>
      你可以在满足上面所述条件的前提下出租和公开展示文档副本。

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>3.大量复制</literal>
</para>
    <para>
      如果你发布的 Document 的印刷副本数量超过100份，并且 
Document 的许可证声明要求 Cover 
Texts，你必须用封面封底包住副本，且其上必须清晰可辨的印有所有的 Cover Texts：包括封面上的 Front-Cover Texts 和封底上的 Back-Cover Texts。封面和封底还都必须写明你是该副本的出版者。封面必须印上完整的书名，书名的每个字都必须一样地突出可见。此外你可以在封面添加一些其它素材。仅仅改动了封面封底的复制，只要他们保留了 Document 的标题并且符合这些条件，从其他方面可视其为原样复制。

    </para>
    
    <para>
      如果封面或封底必要的文字太多，以至于全放上去的话将看不清楚，那么你可以把前面的条目（在保证清楚的前提下尽可能多的）列在封面或封底，剩下的那些放在邻近的页面里。 

    </para>
    
    <para>
      如果你出版或分发 Document 的 Opaque 
副本数量超过100份，那么你必须要么随同每份 Opaque 
副本附带一份机器可读的 Transparent 副本，要么在每份 
Opaque 
副本里或随同该副本指明一个公众可以访问到的计算机网络的地址，使用网络的公众可以用公众标准网络协议从该地址匿名且免费地下载到完全 Transparent 且不包含任何附加材料的 Document 副本。如果你采用后一种办法，你必须适当采取一些慎重的措施，当你开始大量发行 Opaque 副本时，要保证在你（直接或者通过你的代理或零售商）发布最后一份 Opaque 副本后至少一年内，对应版本的 Transparent 副本在指定的地址仍然可以这样访问到。

    </para>
    
    <para>
      希望你可以在大量再次发布 Document 
副本之前与作者取得联系，这虽然不是必需的，但是这样可以给他们一个机会提供给你 Document 的最新版本。 

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>4.修改</literal>
</para>
    <para>
      你可以在上文第2和第3节的条件下复制和发布 Document 的 
Modified Version，只要你严格地依本 License 发布代替了 Document 
的角色的 Modified Version，这样任何持有该 Modified Version 
的一份副本的人都可以对其进行发行和修改。此外，在 
Modified Version 里你必须做如下一些事情： 

    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>A</title>
	  <para>
	    在扉页（和封皮上，如果有的话）使用的书名要不同于 
Document 
的书名，且要不同于先前版本的书名（这些书名，如果有的话，应该是列在 Document 的历史章节里的）。如果某个版本原来的发行者允许，你也可以使用和那个版本相同的书名。 

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>B</title>
	  <para>
	    List on the Title 	 Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities 	 
responsible for authorship of the modifications in the 	 Modified Version, 	 
together with at least five of the principal authors of 	 the Document (all 
of 	 its principal authors, if it has less than five).

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>C</title>
	  <para>
	    State on the Title 	 Page the name of the publisher of the Modified Version, 
as the 	 publisher.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>D</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>E</title>
	  <para>
	    Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications 	 adjacent to the 
other copyright notices.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>F</title>
	  <para>
	    Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a 	 license notice giving 
the public permission to use the 	 Modified Version under 	 the terms of 
this License, in the form shown in the 	 Addendum below.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>G</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and 	 
required Cover 	 Texts given in the Document's license notice.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>H</title>
	  <para>
	    Include an unaltered copy of this License.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>I</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve the section entitled <quote>History</quote>, and 	 its title, and 
add to it an item stating at least the 	 title, year, new authors, and 
publisher of the Modified Version as given on 	 the Title Page.  If 	 there 
is no section entitled <quote>History</quote> in the 	 Document, create one 
	 stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the 	 Document as given 
on its Title Page, then add an item 	 describing the Modified Version as 
stated in the previous 	 sentence.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>J</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for public 
access 	 to a Transparent 	 copy of the Document, and likewise the network 
locations 	 given in the Document for previous versions it was based 	 
on. These may be placed in the <quote>History</quote> 	 section.  You may 
omit a network location for a work that 	 was published at least four years 
before the Document 	 itself, or if the original publisher of the version it 
	 refers to gives permission.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>K</title>
	  <para>
	    In any section entitled <quote>Acknowledgements</quote> or 	 
<quote>Dedications</quote>, preserve the section's title, 	 and preserve in 
the section all the substance and tone of 	 each of the contributor 
acknowledgements and/or 	 dedications given therein.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>L</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve all the Invariant 	 Sections of the Document, unaltered in their 	 
text and in their titles.  Section numbers or the 	 equivalent are not 
considered part of the section titles.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>M</title>
	  <para>
	    Delete any section entitled 	 <quote>Endorsements</quote>. Such a section 
may not be 	 included in the Modified 	 Version.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>N</title>
	  <para>
	    Do not retitle any existing section as 	 <quote>Endorsements</quote> or to 
conflict in title with 	 any Invariant 	 Section.

	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
      If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or appendices 
that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material copied from the 
Document, you may at your option designate some or all of these sections as 
invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in 
the Modified Version's license notice.  These titles must be distinct from 
any other section titles.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may add a section entitled <quote>Endorsements</quote>, provided it 
contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various 
parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text has been 
approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a 
passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list of 
Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one passage of Front-Cover Text 
and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements made by) 
any one entity. If the Document already includes a cover text for the same 
cover, previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity you 
are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may replace the 
old one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher that added the 
old one.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License give 
permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or imply 
endorsement of any Modified Version .

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS</literal>
</para>

    <para>
      You may combine the Document with other documents released under this 
License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified versions, 
provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant Sections 
of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list them all as Invariant 
Sections of your combined work in its license notice.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and multiple 
identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy. If there 
are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different contents, 
make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end of it, in 
parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of that section if 
known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment to the section 
titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the 
combined work.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      In the combination, you must combine any sections entitled 
<quote>History</quote> in the various original documents, forming one 
section entitled <quote>History</quote>; likewise combine any sections 
entitled <quote>Acknowledgements</quote>, and any sections entitled 
<quote>Dedications</quote>.  You must delete all sections entitled 
<quote>Endorsements.</quote>

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</literal>
</para>
    <para>
      You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents 
released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this 
License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in the 
collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for verbatim 
copying of each of the documents in all other respects.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may extract a single document from such a collection, and dispbibute it 
individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this License 
into the extracted document, and follow this License in all other respects 
regarding verbatim copying of that document.

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</literal>
</para>
    <para>
      A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate and 
independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or 
distribution medium, does not as a whole count as a Modified Version of the 
Document, provided no compilation copyright is claimed for the compilation.  
Such a compilation is called an <quote>aggregate</quote>, and this License 
does not apply to the other self-contained works thus compiled with the 
Document , on account of their being thus compiled, if they are not 
themselves derivative works of the Document.  If the Cover Text requirement 
of section 3 is applicable to these copies of the Document, then if the 
Document is less than one quarter of the entire aggregate, the Document's 
Cover Texts may be placed on covers that surround only the Document within 
the aggregate. Otherwise they must appear on covers around the whole 
aggregate.

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>8. TRANSLATION</literal>
</para>

    <para>
      Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may distribute 
translations of the Document under the terms of section 4. Replacing 
Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission from their 
copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or all Invariant 
Sections in addition to the original versions of these Invariant 
Sections. You may include a translation of this License provided that you 
also include the original English version of this License. In case of a 
disagreement between the translation and the original English version of 
this License, the original English version will prevail.

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>9. TERMINATION</literal>
</para>
    <para>
      You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except as 
expressly provided for under this License. Any other attempt to copy, 
modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will 
automatically terminate your rights under this License. However, parties who 
have received copies, or rights, from you under this License will not have 
their licenses terminated so long as such parties remain in full compliance.

    </para>
    
    <para><literal>10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</literal>
</para>
    <para>
      The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of the GNU 
Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions will be 
similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail to 
address new problems or concerns. See http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number. If the 
Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this License 
<quote>or any later version</quote> applies to it, you have the option of 
following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or of 
any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free 
Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version number of 
this License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by 
the Free Software Foundation.

    </para>

    <para><literal>Addendum</literal>
</para>
    <para>
      To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy of the 
License in the document and put the following copyright and license notices 
just after the title page:

    </para>
    
    <blockquote>
      <para>
	Copyright &copy; YEAR YOUR NAME.

      </para>
      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this 	document under 
the terms of the GNU Free Documentation 	License, Version 1.1 or any later 
version published by the 	Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant 
Sections being LIST 	THEIR TITLES, with the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, 
	and with the Back-Cover 	Texts being LIST.  A copy of the license is 
included in 	the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation 
	License</quote>.

      </para>
    </blockquote>
      
    <para>
      If you have no Invariant Sections, write <quote>with no Invariant 
Sections</quote> instead of saying which ones are invariant.  If you have no 
Front-Cover Texts, write <quote>no Front-Cover Texts</quote> instead of 
<quote>Front-Cover Texts being LIST</quote>; likewise for Back-Cover Texts.

    </para>
    
    <para>
      If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we recommend 
releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free software 
license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their use in free 
software.

    </para>
</appendix>  







